A Guide to the Garden Club of Virginia Records, 1923-2008
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Garden Club of Virginia Records, 1923-2008
The Library of Virginia
44888
8.85 cubic feet (21 boxes)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Gift of the Garden Club of Virginia, Richmond.
Historical Information
The Garden Club of Virginia is an active association of forty-seven garden clubs, whose members collectively form a group of more than 3,300 civic leaders from around the Commonwealth. The Garden Club of Virginia exists to celebrate the beauty of the land, to conserve the gifts of nature and to challenge future generations to build on this heritage. It sponsors three major flower shows annually, presents various educational programs, and makes awards to encourage community conservation and beautification projects. Most notably, the Garden Club of Virginia is recognized for its Historic Garden Week, a statewide tour of gardens and homes. Proceeds from the tour are used to fund garden restoration projects throughout Virginia. With over $14.5 million realized since its inception in 1929, the Garden Club of Virginia has restored the gardens at more than fifty properties.
Scope and Content
Records, 1923-2008, of the Garden Club of Virginia, including subject files, information relating to the revision of Homes and Gardens of Old Virginia, publicity files, and publications.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
I. Subject Files.
II. Homes and Gardens of Old Virginia.
III. Publicity Files.
IV. Publications.
Contents List
- Series I. Subject Files, 1930-2006., Extent: 3 boxes. (Box 1-3)
  The subject files contain historical and other information on specific gardens and homes in Virginia that were included on tours during Historic Garden Week, planning files for the event, and articles, drafts, and essays written by Charlotte Taylor Massie (1917-2000). There are also copies of the club's journal and newsletter for various years in this series.
  - Abbotts' Garden (Windsor Farms). (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Agecroft. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Barboursville Visitors' Register, 1930-1940. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Belle Air (Charles City County). (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Berkeley. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bottomley, William Lawrence. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Brandon. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Eastern Shore. (Box 1, Folder 8-10)
  - Executive Mansion. (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Garden Club of Virgina Journal. (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Garden Gossip. (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Garden Retreats: Stopping to Smell the Roses, Henrico County TV (DVD), 2006. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Historic Garden Week - Planning, 1981-1987. (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  - Homes and Gardens of Old Virginia, 1962. (Box 2, Folder 4-6)
  - Information on Estates Open for Historic Garden Week. (Box 2, Folder 7-8)
  - Massie, Charlotte Taylor - Articles, Drafts, Essays. (Box 2, Folder 9-13)
  - "Memories of Garden Week". (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Mount Sterling. (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Nanzatico. (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Pamunkey River and West Point. (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Restorations. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Riverview Farm. (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Roseland Manor. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Sherwood Forest. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Shirley. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Stratford Hall Gardens. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Town and Country. (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Tradescant. (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Upper Brandon. (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Virginia Highway Historical Markers Since 1948. (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Virginia House. (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Westover. (Box 3, Folder 12)
- Series II. Homes and Gardens of Old Virginia, 1966., Extent: 1 box. (Box 4)
  This series of materials concerns publication of the fourth edition of Homes and Gardens of Old Virginia in 1966, and includes tables of contents, drafts of descriptions of homes and gardens to be included in the volume, and correspondence with some of their owners. The files are arranged by area of the state, and were kept by Adelia C. Matthews (1899-1982), who was secretary to the editorial committee.
  - Area 1 - Alexandria and Fairfax County. (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Ares 2 - Warrenton. (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Area 3 - Fauquier, Loudoun, and Culpeper Counties. (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Area 4 - Winchester and Clarke County. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Area 5 - Fredericksburg Area. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Area 6 - Northern Neck. (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Area 7 - Upper James River. (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Area 8 - Hanover County. (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Area 9 - Richmond. (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Area 10 - Lower James River. (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Area 11 - Surry, Southampton, and Isle of Wight Counties. (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Area 12 - Suffolk. (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Area 13 - Williamsburg. (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Area 14 - Yorktown. (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Area 15 - New Kent and King William Counties. (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Area 16 - Gloucester, Mathews, and Middlesex Counties. (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Area 17 - Norfolk and Princess Anne County. (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Area 18 - Eastern Shore. (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Ares 19 - Orange County. (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Area 20 - Albemarle County. (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Area 21 - Staunton. (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Area 22 - Lexington. (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Area 23 - Lynchburg. (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Area 24 - Danville. (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Area 25 - Roanoke. (Box 4, Folder 25)
- Series III. Publicity Files, 1923-2008., Extent: 15 boxes. (Box 5-13, 16-21)
  The majority of the collection consists of publicity files for Historic Garden Week, including newspaper clippings and supplements, magazine articles, brochures, booklets, correspondence, and drafts of articles and press releases prepared for publication in various state and national newspapers and journals. This series is arranged by year. Material for a particular year could be in more than one box, depending on size.
  - 1923. (Box 16, Folder 1)
  - 1929. (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - 1930. (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - 1933. (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - 1936. (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - 1938. (Box 16, Folder 4)
  - 1941. (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - 1941. (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - 1947. (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - 1948. (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - 1949-1954. (Box 5, Folder 5-7)
  - 1950. (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - 1951. (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - 1952. (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - 1953. (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - 1953. (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - 1954. (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - 1955. (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - 1955. (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - 1956. (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - 1957. (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - 1957. (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - 1958. (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - 1958. (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - 1959. (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - 1959. (Box 16, Folder 6)
  - 1959. (Box 20, Folder 6)
  - 1960. (Box 6, Folder 1-3)
  - 1960. (Box 16, Folder 7)
  - 1960. (Box 20, Folder 7)
  - 1961. (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - 1961. (Box 16, Folder 8)
  - 1961. (Box 20, Folder 8)
  - 1962. (Box 6, Folder 5-6)
  - 1962. (Box 16, Folder 9)
  - 1962. (Box 20, Folder 9)
  - 1963. (Box 6, Folder 7-9)
  - 1963. (Box 16, Folder 10)
  - 1963. (Box 20, Folder 10)
  - 1964. (Box 7, Folder 1-2)
  - 1965. (Box 7, Folder 3-6)
  - 1965. (Box 16, Folder 11)
  - 1965. (Box 20, Folder 11)
  - 1966. (Box 7, Folder 7-8)
  - 1966. (Box 16, Folder 12)
  - 1966. (Box 20, Folder 12)
  - 1966-1967. (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - 1967. (Box 16, Folder 13)
  - 1968. (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - 1968. (Box 16, Folder 14)
  - 1968. (Box 20, Folder 13)
  - 1969. (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - 1969. (Box 16, Folder 15)
  - 1969. (Box 20, Folder 14)
  - 1970. (Box 8, Folder 4-5)
  - 1970. (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - 1970. (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - 1971. (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - 1971. (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - 1971. (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - 1972. (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - 1972. (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - 1972. (Box 21, Folder 3)
  - 1973. (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - 1973. (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - 1973. (Box 21, Folder 4)
  - 1974. (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - 1974. (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - 1974. (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - 1975. (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - 1975. (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - 1975. (Box 21, Folder 6)
  - 1976. (Box 9, Folder 1)
  - 1977. (Box 9, Folder 2-3)
  - 1977. (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - 1978. (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - 1979. (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - 1980. (Box 9, Folder 6-7)
  - 1980. (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - 1981. (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - 1981. (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - 1982. (Box 9, Folder 9-10)
  - 1983. (Box 10, Folder 1-2)
  - 1984. (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - 1984. (Box 21, Folder 7)
  - 1985. (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - 1985. (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - 1986. (Box 10, Folder 5-6)
  - 1986. (Box 17, Folder 11)
  - 1987. (Box 10, Folder 7-8)
  - 1987. (Box 21, Folder 8)
  - 1988. (Box 11, Folder 1)
  - 1989. (Box 11, Folder 2-3)
  - 1989. (Box 17, Folder 12)
  - 1989. (Box 21, Folder 9)
  - 1990. (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - 1990. (Box 18, Folder 1)
  - 1990. (Box 21, Folder 10)
  - 1991. (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - 1991. (Box 18, Folder 2)
  - 1991. (Box 21, Folder 11)
  - 1992. (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - 1992. (Box 18, Folder 3)
  - 1992. (Box 21, Folder 12)
  - 1993. (Box 12, Folder 1-3)
  - 1993. (Box 18, Folder 4)
  - 1993. (Box 21, Folder 13)
  - 1994. (Box 12, Folder 4-5)
  - 1994. (Box 18, Folder 5)
  - 1994. (Box 21, Folder 14)
  - 1995. (Box 12, Folder 6-7)
  - 1995. (Box 18, Folder 6)
  - 1995. (Box 21, Folder 15)
  - 1996. (Box 12, Folder 8-10)
  - 1996. (Box 18, Folder 7)
  - 1996. (Box 21, Folder 16)
  - 1997. (Box 12, Folder 11-13)
  - 1997. (Box 18, Folder 8)
  - 1997. (Box 21, Folder 17)
  - 1998. (Box 18, Folder 9)
  - 1999. (Box 18, Folder 10)
  - 2000. (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - 2001. (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - 2001. (Box 21, Folder 18)
  - 2002. (Box 19, Folder 3)
  - 2003. (Box 19, Folder 4)
  - 2004. (Box 19, Folder 5)
  - 2005. (Box 19, Folder 6)
  - 2006. (Box 19, Folder 7)
  - 2007. (Box 19, Folder 8)
  - 2008. (Box 13, Folder 1-2)
  - 2008. (Box 19, Folder 9)
  - n.d.. (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - n.d. (Box 19, Folder 10)
- Series IV. Publications., Extent: 2 boxes. (Box 14-15)
  There are numerous brochures, guidebooks, and other publications on specific historic sites in Virginia and on the subject of gardening.
  - Publications. (Box 14-15)